Narrator: Jack Horton lives in San José in Costa Rica,
where he teaches computer science at a secondary school.
Jack: The first thing that I really noticed
when I arrived here was how incredibly friendly the people are.
The ‘ticos’ – that’s what they’re called – are much friendlier than people in Europe.
They always say buenos días to you even if they don’t know you.
And if something’s good, like a beautiful day or a good meal, they say pura vida, which I love.
It literally means ‘pure life’, but I think it really means ‘things are great’, or something like that.
One thing that can be difficult for foreigners though
is that the sense of time is completely different in Costa Rica – they call it ‘tico time’.
If there is an appointment at, let’s say, seven in the evening, ticos probably leave home at seven o’clock.
But everyone knows it’s OK not to arrive on time and it’s not a problem.
Another thing that surprised me was the weather. I thought Costa Rica was hot and sunny all the time.
That’s true in the dry season, and the temperature’s about twenty-five degrees all year round,
but in the rainy season, especially in September and October, it rains really heavily for maybe two hours a day.
Really amazing rain, nothing like in England.
Everyone told me that the scenery was beautiful in Costa Rica, but it was even more beautiful than I expected.
Incredible animals, birds, trees – and volcanoes.
Some of them are active and smoke quietly, and then suddenly there’s a big bang and they start erupting.
I was quite frightened the first time it happened.
What else? Er, I thought that life here was going to be very cheap,
but in fact, food is very expensive, especially imported food.
The only thing that’s cheap is fruit, vegetables, and coffee – wonderful, wonderful coffee.
And the fruit and vegetables are very different from what we have in Europe.
One day I went to a market and I didn’t recognize any of the fruit.
I like San José. Some people say it can be dangerous, but that’s true of most big cities.
I don’t feel that it is. It is true that some of the roads are terrible, but in general, I really love it here.